<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="get-started">
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <para>Learning a new framework is not always straight forward. In this section, we (the Spring Data team) 
    tried to provide, what we think is, an easy to follow guide for starting with Spring Data Key Value module. 
    Of course, feel free to create your own learning 'path' as you see fit and, if possible, please report back
    any improvements to the documentation that can help others.</para>

    <section id="get-started:first-steps">
		<title>First Steps</title>
		
		<para>As explained in <xref linkend="why-Spring Data-Key Value"/>, Spring Data Key Value (SDKV) provides integration 
		between	Spring framework and key value (KV) stores. Thus, it is important to become acquainted with both of these 
		frameworks (storages or environments depending on how you want to name them). Throughout the SDKV documentation, 
		each section provides links to resources relevant however, it is best to become familiar with these topics beforehand.</para>
		  
		<section id="get-started:first-steps:spring">
			<title>Knowing Spring</title>
			<para>Spring Data uses heavily Spring framework's <ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/reference/spring-core.html">core</ulink> functionality, 
			such as the <ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/reference/beans.html">IoC</ulink> container,
			<ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/reference/resources.html">resource</ulink> abstract or
			<ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/reference/aop.html">AOP</ulink> infrastructure. While it is not important
			to know the Spring APIs, understanding the concepts behind them is. At a minimum, the idea behind IoC should be familiar.
			These being said, the more knowledge one has about the Spring, the faster she will pick Spring Data Key Value.
			Besides the very comprehensive (and sometimes disarming) documentation that explains in detail the Spring Framework,
			there are a lot of articles, blog entries and books on the matter - take a look at the Spring framework
			<ulink url="http://www.springsource.org/documentation">home page</ulink> for more information. In general, this should be the starting point for 
			developers wanting to try Spring DKV.</para>
		</section>
		<section id="get-started:first-steps:nosql">
			<title>Knowing NoSQL and Key Value stores</title>
			<para>NoSQL stores have taken the storage world by storm. It is a vast domain with a plethora of solutions, terms and patterns (to make things worth even the
			term itself has multiple <ulink url="http://www.google.com/search?q=nosoql+acronym">meanings</ulink>).
			While some of the principles are common, it is crucial that the user is familiar to some degree with the stores supported by SDKV.
			The best way to get acquainted to this solutions is to read their documentation and follow their examples - it usually doesn't take more then 5-10 minutes
			to go through them and if you are coming from an RDMBS-only background many times these exercises can be an eye opener. 
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="get-started:first-steps:samples">
			<title>Trying Out The Samples</title>
			<para>Unfortunately the SDKV project is very young and there are no samples available yet. However we are working on them and plan to make them available
			as soon as possible. In the meantime however, one can use our test suite as a code example (assuming the documentation is not enough) - we provide extensive
			integration tests for our code base.
			</para>
			<!-- 
			<para>The current distribution contains:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Simple Service Sample</para>
					<para>A simple example that illustrates OSGi service publication and consumption through Spring DM. This is a good starting point
					for users learning the basics.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Weather Sample</para>
					<para>A demo that shows more advanced features of Spring DM and OSGi. The application creates a very simple weather information services 
					presenting some best practices in designing an application to take advantage of the modularity offered by OSGi.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Simple Web App Sample</para>
					<para>As the name implies, this is a simple web application, containing Servlets, JSPs and JSP tags, that runs inside OSGi through Spring DM.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Web Console Sample</para>
					<para>A more complicated sample that demos a Spring MVC annotation based, web application that runs inside OSGi through Spring DM, featuring 
					class path scanning and various Spring taglib. Additionally, the web application interacts with the OSGi environment through the web UI.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist> 
			<para>Each project contains instructions regarding its content and startup procedure. Users are encouraged to experiment with the samples to get a better
			understanding of the technologies used.</para>
			 -->
		</section>
	</section>
    
    <section id="get-started:help">
		<title>Need Help?</title>
		
		<para>If you encounter issues or you are just looking for an advice, feel free to use one of the links below:</para>
		
		<section id="get-started:help:community">
  		    <title>Community Support</title>
			<para>The Spring Data <ulink url="http://forum.springframework.org/forumdisplay.php?f=80">forum</ulink> is a message board for all Spring Data (not just Key Value) users to
			share information and help each other. Note that registration is needed <emphasis>only</emphasis> for posting.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="get-started:help:professional">
  		    <title>Professional Support</title>
			<para>Professional, from-the-source support, with guaranteed response time, is available from <ulink url="http://www.springsource.com">SpringSource</ulink>,
			the company behind Spring Data and Spring.  
			</para>
		</section>
    </section>
    
    <section id="get-started:up-to-date">
		<title>Following Development</title>
		
		<para>For information on the Spring Data source code repository, nightly builds and snapshot artifacts please see the Spring Data home 
		<ulink url="http://www.springsource.org/spring-data">page</ulink>.   
		</para>
		<para>You can help make Spring Data best serve the needs of the Spring community by interacting with developers through the Spring Community 
		<ulink url="http://forum.springsource.org">forums</ulink>.</para>
		<para>If you encounter a bug or want to suggest an improvement, 
		please create a ticket on the Spring Data issue <ulink url="https://jira.springframework.org/browse/DATAKV">tracker</ulink>.</para>
		<para>To stay up to date with the latest news and announcements in the Spring eco system, subscribe to the 
		Spring Community <ulink url="http://www.springframework.org/">Portal</ulink>.</para>
		<para>Lastly, you can follow the SpringSource Data <ulink url="http://blog.springsource.com/category/data-access/">blog</ulink> or the project team on Twitter 
		(<ulink url="http://twitter.com/costinl">Costin</ulink>)</para>
	</section>
    
</chapter>